Oh Vasudeva suitum our new Ramadan um
dave aqui para maana and krishna monday
jagadguru can you hear me can everybody
hear me at the back I don't know why I I
can't hear myself oh now now it's okay
yeah yeah
before we start we had I had a very
interesting experience this evening
there's this a conference at NYU in the
philosophy department on the hard
problem of consciousness many of you
know what it is thanks to me I've been
going on and on boring you about it and
today the discussion was the Advaita
Vedanta answer to it and so a professor
from Australia all the way from
Australia Miri Albahari she came and she
gave a talk some of us we went to attend
if some of you are here who we went we
were there together they were thinking
were these strange people so imagine the
top people in in philosophy especially
in philosophy for my net block and
others I mean these are names to be
reckoned with
so did a very where there and what we
are studying here that was being
presented therein in more philosophical
language when the presentation was going
on I was so delighted you know the
things that she was saying are almost if
you put them in Sanskrit that's exactly
what Shankar Acharya was saying 1400
years ago exactly the same things not
only that it's a tough crowd somebody
said it's a tough sell obviously there
you don't expect them to buy it or
immediately big to take up take it up
but even the questions they asked in the
hard questions they asked they don't
know exactly those questions have been
asked by the opponents of the ad
weddings over the last 1400 years and
there are excellent
to them I'm not saying that it's all
solved and cut and right of course not
but I think there are good answers to
that in fact afterwards I was talking to
some of the philosophers and saying that
you're trying to put me out of a job I
was feeling happy and the same time as a
feeling I said I thought maybe I should
retire go back to the Himalayas the
Americans can take care of themselves
now they are doing it in the in NYU so
why should I
where should we have a Balanta Society
for it incredible I was so happy to see
this in fact what we are going to talk
about today is directly related to the
discussions that was going on at that
time
and as a result is a sort of consequence
of that I nearly did not make it to the
class I came out of NYU then I got went
into Washington Park and then I came out
and I got lost so I wandered around a
little bit here and there with time
running out for the class and I thought
no need to get anxious because nothing's
going to happen unless I get there so
yeah nothing interesting is going to
happen unless I reach but I did manage
to come back I said last time that the
verse that we are going to do now the
sixteenth verse second chapter is a very
important verse and philosophically
speaking at least from the non-dual
perspective it's the heart of the
bhagavad-gita I'm using my words
carefully philosophically speaking from
the non-dual perspective if you are
asking for practical advice in spiritual
life there other verses which will be
very useful for karma yoga something
like karma Nevada car a state that is a
central verse what do i do I don't want
all this philosophy how do I lead my
life Krishna will say at the very end
sort of a sermon particular give up all
of the practices take refuge in me so
practical spiritual advice there are
other verses this will seem very
theoretical but this is fundamental to
the whole of Advaita Vedanta this verse
what does this verse say it can be said
easily the central teaching of Advaita
Vedanta Brahman is real the world is an
appearance and you are Brahman many men
you feel
yeah we know that you should have been
there the seminar just each of these
things is taken was taken up and
shredded the person coming from say a
materialist reductionist background this
is a crazy thing to say incredible thing
to say but this is the central message
of Advaita Vedanta Shri Ramakrishna he
was asked please teach me spirituality
in one sentence so the person who asked
that was wise because otherwise the
whole of the gospel of ramakrishna was
several hundred pages eight hundred nine
hundred pages is the teaching of
ramakrishna but one sentence tell me all
of spirituality in one sentence and sri
ramakrishna looked at that man and he
said Brahman is real the world is an
appearance assimilate this truth and
then the writer no less than Swami
Ramananda he says saying this sri
ramakrishna kept quiet he says this also
that means emphasizes it that Saddam
Krishnan did not add anything more to it
Brahman is the reality the world is an
appearance in Bengal he said ated
Honaker did assimilate this this is
enough word for for enlightenment this
verse says it this verse is for the
first time what is going on here krishna
is talking about the vedanta theory of
this self who are we and he has said
that we do not die with the death of the
body remember the last few verses but
now he is coming to the the central
teaching there is one reality which
appears as this universe and you are
that reality brahma satyam brahman is
real jagat mithya the universe is an
appearance and what about you
Jeeva from heaven opera you are none
other than that that absolute reality I
was thinking to make you smile the
language the professor was using to say
exactly this thing
she was saying that Advaita says that is
an a perspectival ground of
consciousness and that appears as
perspectival subjects basically this is
the same thing this central teaching
that has been set forth for the first
time in this verse and as you can
imagine Shankar Acharya the great
teacher of Advaita Vedanta he is very
very happy with this verse so today we
are going to not only read the verse and
the basic meaning behind it but I'm
going to take you into what I usually do
not do into the original commentary of
Shankar Acharya on this verse so we will
do a close reading of his comment - it's
fantastic and it has tremendous
implications for for philosophy the
commentary' itself is so wonderful and
the great thing is not only is the truth
stated here teaching given here it is
argued out and it is also shown how you
can directly experience it here and now
and forever so that's what's given here
there's a story which goes you know
Mahabharata was written by Vyasa the
great poet and sage and remember the
story of very nice story says
Mahabharata he needed somebody to take
it down here to write it down a what you
call a stenographer a scribe and so who
does it get Ganesha
so Ganesha is described in with his
elephant head energies his enormous
processing capacity he is described and
we are says is the person who's
composing and giving out poetry as it
comes to him all in the form of poetry
and this greatest of all epics but we
also knew that or Ganesha sets up a sets
a condition I will write it down but you
have to keep on composing and telling me
the verses it can't be like you can't
take a break and I'll keep writing if
the moment you stop
I will also stop and the moment I stop
that's it I'm done
Vyasa is no less he said okay I agree to
your conditions but I have a condition
of my own and the condition is if there
is okay the condition is you must
understand what you are writing
you must understand before before you
write it down once you have understood
it write it down don't write without
understanding and on purpose the answer
would once in a while
compose a verse very difficult to
understand so that Ganesha would go
mm-hmm and we also would take a breath
of breather you-know-who but very soon
Ganesha latinum got it when he starts
writing so there are those verses to
this story with just a story to show
that there are difficult verses they
call not grunty and they are the places
where you have to really pay attention
because something deep is being said
said here untie it at that point the
whole thing becomes revealed to you one
of those verses is there are others you
will often find them by their
deceptively simple appearance and yet
paradoxical statement and sometimes
paradoxical or here it will seem
tautological stating the absolute
obvious so what does he mean let's see
please repeat after me
Nasser to videotape abu nasr to
videotape ha na vidyate esata
Vidya ha ha
rapid rich tone rapid rich 22 Anna you
start or - if he he started to add a
shape he the unreal never comes into
existence and the real never goes out of
existence
those who are truly wise they have
understood these two the Unreal as the
Unreal and the real as the real those
who are truly wise they have understood
now in the face of it it's strangely
what philosophers called tautological
stating the obvious one is one is a it's
not illogical that you're stating the
obvious real is real underneath unreal
is unreal that's all it's wise to not
know what is real and what is unreal I
have to go a little deeper what does he
want to say here this is the philosophy
of being the philosophy of existence
remember there can be an approach to
Brahman
from sucked existence from chit
consciousness and also from onon the
value or bliss this is an exist this is
an approach from existence
what is from isness now one way I'll
give you a simple explanation before we
launch into what Shankar Acharya does
one explanation is this one way of
explaining it is this
I have often mentioned you can think of
it in this way things have intrinsic
properties and incidental properties so
I've often given you the example of a
hot potato potato which is being boiled
so it's hot but it's hot only
temporarily it was not hot to begin with
and it will not be hot a little later
it's only when you're serving it hot now
it gains heat and loses heat so the heat
and the potato it's not it's not
intrinsic to the potato it's not always
hot where did it get its heat from it's
a borrowed heat it got it seeped from
the boiling water and the boiling water
similarly is not intrinsically hot it is
hot now but it was not hot earlier and
it will not be hot later on that he does
not belong to the water it borrowed it
from the hot pan similarly the pan it
well it was cold it borrowed its heat
from the fire underneath but the fire
did not borrow its heat from anywhere
else
it has its own its intrinsic heat now
look at notice what happens to the fire
as long as it is burning it is hot it
will use a very simple example it is hot
it does not become hot and does not
become cold as long as the fire is there
it is hot
and it can lend its heat to others so a
sign of a borrowed property incidental
property accidental property is that it
comes and goes
the pan was cold it became hot and lost
the heat the water became hot and lost
the heat the the potato it became hot
and lost the heat but the fire never
became not a hot and Lassa heat whenever
it was there it was hot so this sign of
an intrinsic property is that it does
not come and go the sign of an
incidental property you know what is
meant by incidental not essential to the
nature of the thing it's borrowed it
comes and goes so somebody says in
Manhattan you don't know who's rich
because everybody acts rich and spends a
lot of money but some they own that
money someday it's they're running on
their maxing out their credit cards so
only when it's repossessed the people
who have lent you money they come to
take away the stuff then you realize oh
it was borrowed money it came and went
but it does not belong to that person
similarly about heat now if this is this
much you take away this much if there is
something called an intrinsic property
it will be there always if there is
something called an accidental or
incidental property it can come and go
the sign of it being an incidental
properties it comes and goes
now think of existence can existence be
a property that's a different issue
altogether because there's a lot of
philosophy we might not know it
philosophers would immediately object
but anyway consider existence suppose
existence is an incidental property I'm
telling you something which is common
sense but I'm putting it in a little
philosophical language suppose existence
is an incidental property what would
happen to it if heat is and what
happened to the heat in the potato or
the water of the pan it comes and goes
if existence were like that it would
come and go when heat comes and goes the
object becomes hot and cold if existence
comes and goes what would happen to the
object
it would be born it would die or to be
created it would it would come into
being it would go out of being right are
you with me if existence is like that if
it comes if something gains existence
it's a it's a fancy way of saying it is
created or born if something loses
existence it's a philosophical way of
saying that it is destroyed or dead
which means being born and dying being
created and destroyed coming into being
and disappearing these are signs that
this these entities have borrowed
existence existence does not belong to
them incidental the incidental existence
accidental existence borrowed existence
existence does not belong to them and
what are we talking about just about
everything in the world including here
are us our bodies everything is created
products are created bodies are created
and destroyed the entire universe in
fact was created in the Big Bang and
every artifact in it is created and
destroyed every entity that we know
comes into being and is lost so they do
not have existence as an intrinsic
property but suppose there is something
called that something which has
existence as an intrinsic property
suppose what would happen to it what
would happen to it it would be there
always it would never be born never die
just as fire whenever fire is there fire
is hot in the same way if existence were
an intrinsic property then that entity
would be there always what he's saying
here is there is such a thing which has
existence as an intrinsic property and
it's you the real you and he will show
it now he will demonstrate it he says he
it's actually we it is there it's an
open secret not exactly in front of our
noses and we would rather we have to say
behind our noses let us say it's there
all the time an open secret we just have
to see it he's going to show us now so
that's the whole story behind it he was
going to show
what we call our immortal soul that we
are Brahman he's going to show that to
us okay he said the Unreal has no
existence and it does not come into
existence and the real never goes out of
existence he uses words asset and subtle
now there are think of three kinds of
entities one is in Advaita Vedanta which
has intrinsic existence that means it
never goes out of existence it always is
you would say that it's good to say such
a thing you've defined it is there
actually such a thing yes there is we'll
see today right today we will see he
right here there is such a thing and
it's been within everybody's experience
now that thing is that ultimate reality
is Brahman is such that the name for
that is such pure being existence pure
being sucked so uses that word sucked we
are we have also heard sat-chit-ananda
brahman is defined as existence
consciousness place so that word is used
sucked that is the ultimate reality the
opposite of that is the absolutely
unreal which has no existence at all so
like a square circle for example or the
classical example they give is banda
hapara the son of a barren woman by
definition impossible a square circle by
definition impossible so something that
can never that does not exist and can
never appear does not exist cannot
appear there's no question of it
experiencing such a thing it's a logical
impossibility but in between these two
the absolutely real and the totally
unreal in between these two there's
another category which has borrowed
existence so which comes into existence
and disappears
that's that in-between category in
Vedanta is called mithya things with
borrowed existence things which do are
not intrinsically real they borrow their
reality for a time being Mattia what is
the difference between
absolutely real and this this in-between
category this English translation would
be the false would be an appearance so
do false how do you distinguish between
existence that which really exists such
and this mithya such always exists never
goes out of existence and the myth here
is something which does not exist yet
appears to exist for a time bling with
borrowed existence where does it borrow
his existence from it borrows its
existence from subtle
I'll repeat mithya the false the the
apparent reality who in for a time being
it appears before us the absolutely
unreal never appears as nobody has
actually seen a square circle but we
have this is not not crazy because we
have such experiences Mirage water in
the Mirage it you see it seems like
existing there when you go close you see
it doesn't exist the classic example of
seeing a snake in a rope so it appears
for a moment you saw it so it's not you
saw it but when you go close it's not
there so there is a category of things
which are which appear without existing
and for the time being they seem to
exist and their existence is borrowed so
that category is called mithya and
Shankar Acharya wants to say whatever we
experience in the world is in that
category they all have borrowed
existence they do not exist by
themselves they will not exist after
some time and even when most important
even when they seem to exist when they
seem to appear before you right now they
do not exist by themselves they are
borrowing their existence from such from
Brahman all right how is this possible
he takes this track see this verse is
about reality and unreality such the
technical term is mithya the word he
uses for Mattia here is assert why this
has to be said is those have studied
Vedanta for them Asad does not mean
meteor
they talk about absolutely real set the
false mithya and the totally unreal ASET
so here does not mean totally unreal is
what I wanted to point out here a set
means false when you say the world is
false Shankar Acharya is calling it a
set here but in Vedanta textbooks a set
means square circle nothing he does not
mean that so that's what has to be clear
all right now we go into we know enough
to go into Shankar Acharya explanation
he takes what yes yes yes all entities
which are called meteor products of maya
maya presents brahman this up the pure
being as the ever-changing world yeah so
therefore everything that we see here
everything that Shankaracharya calls
mithya is maya in fact it's a common
phrase in india sub my ahead people will
repeat repeated in villages they have
not gone through all this philosophy but
it's just a sort of you know catch
phrase you know like life is like that
so sub maya everything is my literally
it means everything is maya but when
somebody says that he's what he or she
means in india is just let it go it's
just like that and don't start
philosophizing with that person he will
be puzzled him all right now the track
Shankar Acharya takes is how do you
borrow existence it's cool to talk about
borrowing existence as if but is it
possible is what do you mean borrow
existence it happens all the time where
does it happen cause and effect material
cause and effect so clay clay when you
shape it into a pot you call it a part
but the pot which has a name a distinct
form and they use name form use nama
Rupa bhava Hara but its entire existence
depends on the constituent clay true or
false only a few of you seem convinced
a clay pot look at this
a wooden lecture a wooden lectern its
entire existence depends upon the would
constitute and constituting it proof
take away the would electron would
disappear immediately right it has no
existence in fact when I touch it what
do I say touch would I don't say touch
lectern well I know I'm touching would
only way I can conventionally see I'm
touching a lectern or a podium but I
know physically I'm testing what the
material the material out of which it is
made so entire existence of this piece
of furniture is the wood constituting it
the material cause the wood is called
the material cause in Sanskrit
Hoopa Donna Karan and this using Shankar
Acharya sturms we will see now this
podium would be called karyam effect Ark
he says vicara vicara means a
modification of the material so the
podía podium is a modification of the
Constituent wood any modification this
is what he wants to say any modification
borrows existence from its constituent
material whether with those I'm enjoying
this but those who are thinking I wanted
some religion let me go and get me some
religion in my life
whatever whatever landed up in don't
worry all that will come devotion and
meditation and ethics all of those
things will come slowly but this is the
central teaching so what have we got so
far
anything that is a modification an
effect depends on its material cause for
its existence it borrows a clay bar
apart borrows existence from the in
constituent clay this furniture borrows
this existence from the constituent wood
all right I'll read out the original
Sanskrit you will like it I translate of
course Shankar Acharya says Ricardo he
saw any entity you see is an effect
modification Ricardo chubby a maturity
effects keep changing the atharva tardy
some solemn Chuck's ishani rupiah mana
mid-victorian a new look a new Paulo a
new palabra hey asset he says just as a
pot which you can see with your eyes
that you can see the form with your eyes
yet there'll be nothing left there if
you take away the clay you will not
perceive anything at all if the clay is
taken away other than the clay you
cannot see the pot other than the pot
can you see the clay yes you can see it
as a lump of clay if you break the pot
you can see it is a broken pot the clay
in the clay you can see in fact all you
are saying seeing is clay literally
anything that your eyes are contacting
is the clay itself okay so what did he
say
just like he gives an example they never
see he says yatta it means just like
just like the form of a clay seen by the
eyes is not seen other than the a form
of a pot seen by the eyes is not seen
other than the clay constituting the pot
without that no pot
similarly what does he want to say
similarly guitar just like that so in
when some chair encourages writing in
sanskrit come in trees if there is a
yatta yatta means just like look for the
tata just like that there is going to
make his point tata sorrow movie car a
car and a battery can undo pull up they
assert a son just like that every effect
every product Bakara
has no existence cannot be found cannot
be experienced without their constituent
material this is the he says a son this
this is the very definition of falsity
so what is this conclusion being an
effect being unable to exist being
unable none Abel Forex unavailable for
experience unavailable for experience
without its constituent cause all these
products are false the term he uses
asset in some in plural asana in
sanskrit plural
also these ones did not exist before
their creation and will not exist after
the destruction remember was not hot
earlier will not be hot afterwards is it
getting hot do you need the fan some
borrowed he says janma pad banks are
beyond problems on open up day not only
are they not existent without their
constituent materials but before their
creation also you could not see them and
after their creation also they are not
available for experience after the
destruction before destruction was not
there before creation was not there
after destruction will not be there even
when we say they are there they are not
there without their constituent material
so this name and form
all these things are names and forms
these names and forms are appearances
they are not there before they were
created they will not be there after
they're gone and even when they are
there there's still appearances of their
underlying material cause but you will
say yes so the clay is there right but
the clay is not there apart from its
cause in the Sanskrit in the old
cosmology how is everything
the clay will not exist apart from the
earth element they talked about sky fire
space fire water air earth so five
elements and today you can talk about
matter as we understand it so he says so
the clay does not exist without its
cause and that one does not exist
without its cause the clay is an
appearance of it so if it's called and
that causes an appearance of its
underlying cause and that is an
appearance of its underlying cause so he
says neither
they etcetera are clay and the whole
sequence because the first one cannot be
experienced without its underlying
reality underlying cause and that one
cannot be experienced without its
underlying substance and so on the whole
thing becomes an appearance then
question so the guy who asked the
question is very interesting often just
the question which comes to maybe if
you're following carefully the same
question will come to your mind are you
saying everything will disappear then da
da ba HSR evolved our person in great
detail they say wait just a minute if
you say that if you do that then we are
we are arriving at nothingness is
everything from A to Z an appearance
that cannot be the thing whole thing
must be grounded somewhere you cannot
infinitely borrow hit it must have come
from something which hasn't RINs which
is intrinsically hot similarly what is
intrinsically existence existing Shankar
Acharya says no it's not that everything
is false
or everything is an appearance there is
and ground reality they are coming there
now what is the ground reality he says
every experience you have in every
experience a pot experience a table
experience man or woman or sky or earth
whatever experience you have good and
bad and pleasant and unpleasant in all
the experiences there are two components
this is very important there are two
components what are the two components
the there is the object of experience
it's called vishaya
sight sound smell taste touch these are
the objects of sense experience and
there is the experience of easeness
which we ignore you see when you see
what I what are you seeing you say
o'clock what are you seeing now you see
a book what are you seeing now you say
hand what Shankar Acharya says no no in
each of these experiences the two
components are there clock name-and-form
clock is so clock is one experience and
the other part of it is it exists it is
do you experience it as existing or
non-existing exist use it goes without
saying
what was your experience cock clock is
book is hand is he says notice the
objects of experience kept changing
clock book hand the objects are
different the clock is not a book the
book is not a hand and the objects come
and go they keep changing sometimes you
see sometimes you hear sometimes you
smell taste touch and what you see keeps
change changing how many things you have
seen since the morning throughout your
lifetimes how many things you have heard
these keep changing but everywhere you
have the continuous unchanging
experience of business now this
continuous unchanging experience of
business very important this is a
doorway to Brahma Yana it is
continuously available to us open it
walk through Vedanta is over for you
finished right now
ya don't need anything else but keep
coming to the class anyway does not work
for you 80 there are 18 chapters so much
of a dancer I think enough for the next
few years so this doorway
what is the doorway I'll repeat again
yours here is her our own continuous
experience of existence its whose
existence your existence could be mine
could be anything that you see all the
time we have an experience of existence
now next he says these two experiences
we have experience of the object and the
experience of existence now when you
experience something the experience is
in you and what you are experiencing is
out there common sense I'm experiencing
a clock so I have an experience of a
clock in my awareness in my mind and
there is a clock out there you see where
this is going so if you are experiencing
a clock
and there's a club there and you have an
experience of a clock if you're
experiencing clock is that isness
experience corresponds to an easiness
reality then you think there's a you
feel there's a clock here is a clock
there's a clock in your mind of the
clock outside clock is that experience
of easiness in your mind in yourself and
that corresponds to an easiness outside
in every item which you see he says
there are two experiences the object
itself and isness and they correspond to
a reality there is an object and there
is isness also now he says the object
keeps changing they have borrowed
existence the sense of easiness does not
change everywhere any experience you
have you have the feeling of being
business then that isness which you in
is there in every object outside that
unchanging isness is that intrinsic
existence we are talking about that does
not borrow exist existence from anything
else that lends existence to everything
remember it may sound abstract we're
actually talking about our living
experience every moment of our life is
analyzing it that feeling of easiness
corresponds to a realist Ness which is
there always that does not come and go
so that which comes and goes we have
already defined it as at appearance that
does not come and go such reality what
is such a reality that sense of isness
corresponding to that there is a reality
everywhere all the time
let's read he says
yuck vishaya buddha nabiyev a charity
that sucked that entity about which your
experience does not change that is
reality yet which i above every charity
taught us at ET the object about which
your experience keeps changing clock
hand book that one is an appearance why
because that has borrowed existence it
is saga sattvam Hollywood didn't trace
it today he says in this way in all our
experiences which experience every
experience you have in life till now and
what you will continue to have you will
have a continuous mixed experience of
appearance and reality appearance and
reality such assert what is appearance
names and forms what is reality is Ness
what do you mean by isness track your
own experience that sense of being a
stick to em Ness okay then he gives an
example son kata son pata son has the
ETA vom serve etre pot exists clot
exists elephant exists shankara shankara
cheerios context 1400 years ago yes so
those are the common we might say SUV
exists that's the closest you can get to
the elephant sir exists then he says is
is is do you notice tayo bao guitar
about the baby charity the touch of that
shit I'm not too sad booty and in these
experiences you will see the object
keeps changing the sense of business
does not change we Club them together
and we never notice the background
business Shankar Acharya is drawing our
attention you think can it be that
simple it's not but in essence it is
pretty simple this is the smog guitar D
Buddha be Shia asan which are art not to
subdivision AB AB AB B which are out
there for that which corresponds to your
changing experience
clock book
and these are appearances why because
they change what is that what's the
problem is a change if they change their
borrowed existence they cannot be real
in themselves but your experience your
experience
everybody's continuous experience of
easiness points toward it's not itself
the reality it points to the reality
which cannot be expressed it points to a
reality why is it that real because it
does not change you never see it coming
into being you never see it disappearing
which one am I talking about
it is ness am-ness in sanskrit a spit to
citta septum in Hindi means power
but if here it means existence being now
the person who's objecting is a funny
guy he's got all the good tough
questions so he says that's cool but
I've got questions number one got a
winner stay got about the questions you
will sometimes never think about also
he's a really smart guy got a winner
stake heard about though via char on
Cambodia charity I teach eight he says
just a minute you said pot exists and
you're making a distinction between the
pot name and form and the existence of
it okay this yes but then when the part
is broken pot does not exist a pot
experience goes and I say existence also
is gone because part is broken part is
gone now so your existence is not you
you what will you say pot is not so your
ace has become is not what do you say to
that
he says na patada WAP is a good
deduction op he says no but you can see
it in the clock you can the elephant
that isness continues the isness
continues it's only the pot name and
form which has disappeared then the
questioner asks a similar question and
it says just a minute so that would be
what got a book deal we gotta answer the
shitty teach it says he's funny he says
that or you say existence the experience
of easiness continues because if the
part is broken the clot is you're saying
but then I can say that this part is
broken but my experience of part
continues in another pot so part is the
ultimate reality well everywhere there's
pop art in this part I cannot say it's a
part anymore but just like you said plot
is elephant is I can say this the other
part is here is a part here is a parts
apart continues so part is real part is
the ultimate reality that will become a
pot Vedanta Shankar Acharya says nah but
are the other show not because you
cannot see you don't have the experience
of a part in a clock you don't have
experience of a part in an elephant but
you have the experience of isness in
whatever exists if you say there is
something in which the experience of
business is not there immediately it
will not exist it is not you see
logically speaking he won't let go
he's like a bulldog he's got hold off in
this he is going he said just a minute
let me clarify this so would the
European us take hurt another chef he'll
teach it you said isness is everywhere
here's a very important point coming up
you said isness is everywhere fine but
when the pot is destroyed
you said clot exists elephant exists but
in the destroyed pot I don't see isness
I can no longer say pot is that part is
gone so there I don't season is where is
the easiness but it's the is it's not a
superficial question suppose somebody
asks suppose everything in the universe
is destroyed before the Big Bang or
after the dissolution of the universe in
Hinduism we talk about cycles of
existence so there will be times when
the universe does not exist pralaya the
cosmic resolution nothing is there then
there is your existence in the absence
of all things where is your existence
just like that in the absence of one pot
where did your precious existence go
because we are saying is part is not
then he says important point now vishay
Hamid Dabashi vitiation of ashati wishes
job how they vitiation on Oh poppet Oh
King
Ishod not open aha Davey Shabbat okay
he says the only way we can actually
experience this is ness is in
association with a name and form why
because that is ness is not really out
there it's you yourself the pure subject
all those things which you experience
they borrow their isness from your own
sense of being but to experience them
you need an entity outside electricity
is everywhere but suppose you say all
the bulbs and the fans are they are all
taken away no electrical appliances
electricity is still there but how do
you know it unless something is spinning
something is magnifying sound something
is shining you will not know the
presence of electricity similarly to
when all entities are destroyed it's not
that existence is gone but existence has
no more instances it still continues it
still continues I used an example of
light once I was talking about this in
Nollan the University in not the old
destroyed one there's a new one in there
so they had a seminar on Buddhism and
Hinduism and Jainism philosophies of
consciousness so I was saying an
analogous thing consciousness is
appreciated understood experienced when
you have something to be conscious of if
there is an object you feel I am
experiencing it if there are no objects
to experience it's not that
consciousness is disappeared it's that
there's nothing to experience so
experience of things has stopped so how
to explain that I was thinking how to
illustrate it and there was conference
in a PowerPoint projector so the
PowerPoint projector and the light
there's an intense beam of light the
funny thing about that beam of light is
you can see the picture on the screen
but the the camera is there or the
projector is up there on the ceiling you
know what I'm talking about you have
seen from there to the screen an intense
night is coming but if you see there
doesn't seem to be anything particular
it's only when the speaker the presenter
is walking through that beam suddenly
you see the face shining with white
light awesome so what I said is right
now in this spot there doesn't seem to
be light it's just air but when I thrust
my hand in there you see my hand shines
with light and it removed my hand what
happens to the light there it's still
there but it's not shining because an
object is not there when the object is
there the light one year it reflects and
you see the object when Swami put it
very beautifully what does the light do
for the object it reveals the object
what does the object we know this but
what does the object do for the light it
manifests an already existing light is
it true right here you see I can show a
little bit here also see if I remove it
there's a light here when I put my hand
you see how it's shining that light
reveals my hand but my hand manifests an
already-existing light similarly names
and forms manifest an always existing
consciousness always existing existence
being without the names and forms the
being is still there but there is no way
of experiencing it that's what he's
saying now an another important question
is raised I am racing through it sort of
I'm skipping a little bit
so you are saying that existence is the
reality and the objects are appearances
to put it in more terms we are used to
existence means Brahman Brahman is
reality and objects means world the
world is false or universe is false or
in sanskrit brahma satyam jagat mithya
do you see how we have led up to that
you're saying this the same entity in
that you are saying the names and forms
are appearances the existence alone is
real real because it is unchanging the
existence alone is real and it manifests
these names and forms it reveals or it
it gives existence lends existence to
the object that's what you are saying
but this reality and falsity they cannot
exist together how can the same thing be
true and false at the same time how can
the same thing with true and false at
the same time this mic is it true or
false true or false
the answer will be depends you're asking
from the point of view Brahman existence
yes it is you're asking about the mic
name and form without the existence it
is not Shankar Acharya gives an example
now I remove the committee Maricha do
any other of Xavier epistemological
nahusha not the smart day Hadi is on the
search Shekhar and acetone of it deity
vomiting he says in a mirage you see two
things at the same time you say this is
water now two things are there that
sense of this and water water is not
there the water that you see there is an
appearance but there is something there
a hot air and the deserts and that's
there so when you see this it points to
a reality and when you say water that's
wrong that water is not there so a
reality and an appearance exist together
coexist together yeah
a real desert and real water cannot
coexist but a real desert desert I'm in
the sandy one not the cake I can never
get the pronounciations desert es desert
yes you you one no is very funny
there was a very senior Swami in st.
Louis he came to this country in the
1930s nineteen to thirty Swami said
prakasananda ji he came to his country
long time ago and I went to say
influence in the Vedanta Society there
the the room where that Swami is to stay
they have kept it exactly like that so
they don't disturb it guests are allowed
to stay there guest Swami's so
everything is there like the way it was
in the he died in the 1970s I think 70s
so everything is the way it was fifty
years ago
so I was sort of a rummaging around and
in one of the dryers I saw a little
notebook with pencil in written in the
1930s the Swami was trying to learn
English American English in those days
so one page says with the English word
and the Bengali meanings desert desert
desert three things in Bengal it's
written more Oh Bhoomi this is the sandy
place and the other one is the sweet
thing which you eat and the other one
and the third one is what you deserve
you get what you deserve and the whole
notebook was painstakingly written with
full of words from the dictionary which
he was trying to learn so he's a certain
courage area says desert is real when
you say this there is something real
there but the water is not real but what
was your experience this is water one
part of it is false one part of his
correct
you say book is book is an appearance is
necessary is Ness
there's an isness running through all
our experiences then he says therefore
body-mind external universe all of them
they are appearances why there are
products and the product or other
modifications they have no existence
apart from their underlying causes and
the underlying causes have no existence
apart from their underlying causes all
the way down to business itself they are
all coming and changing and going but
ultimately down to business itself
tatata at Manoa bhava video monitor now
video teaser wat Revere which are oddity
of achhamma
therefore have we said that isness is a
the absence of that isness cannot be
conceived of what is that isness it is
you it's not really an easiness out
there objects time-space all of them
time is space is objects object is
universe is time-space universe all are
appearances of Maya that underlying
isness is the is the stage on which the
drama takes place is the screen on which
the movie of the universe is playing and
that screen you are that thou art
[Music]
philosophy how does it affect me it is
the highest spiritual practice highest
spiritual practice I was just reading
Swami began on and the g1 the disciples
of sri ramakrishna he is saying to many
people many many years after sri
ramakrishna passed away he said k shops
in who was a great social reformer in
india in those days very well-known
Brahmo Samaj so and he was very well
known because yet actually traveled to
England and met the Queen in those days
so Sri Ramakrishna says to him you have
crossed the oceans and seen many lands
so many things you have seen have you
not seen my divine mother who'd
underlies everything in the universe and
yoga duration my mother who is the
reality of the entire universe have you
not seen her do you not have eyes to see
her
what does he mean by that it is this is
Ness awareness which is the divine
mother
Swami began the explaining after that he
says go on in spiritual life advance
advance you will see a vast radiance
surrounding you all the time and you
will playfully like a fish swimming in
the ocean ocean you will playfully you
know swim in this in this vast equal to
the vast radiance it's here right now we
don't have eyes to see it
what is that vast radiance it is nothing
other than the infinite unlimited isness
awareness the non dualist
see we say our language is meant for
practical use so it's a dualistic
language table is book is the clock is
you know what the non Duras would like
to say is nest tables here business
clocks here business books here it's not
as silly as it appears if you look at
the ocean a child might say oh that wave
has lot of water in it this wave is
small one is less water in it which is
more logical to say that waves have
water in them or the water is appearing
as waves waves do not have water in them
it is the water which appears in various
waves the waves arise in water play
about in water disappear back into water
their names and forms and activities in
water the water is absolutely one
vastness there in the same way like
water can you conceive of can you
conceive of existence as an ocean now
you see with new eyes look around you
see existence as an ocean in which all
people all animals all living and
non-living things including the stars
and the planets they are all waves in
this ocean of existence ashtavakra says
my Ananda Muhammad Oh Vishu Avicii swaha
Vata who they to us Tamayo to Nami with
Dina Bach shotty now you'll understand
in me the infinite ocean of existence
the
waves of the universe arise and subside
let the waves arise I gain nothing
thereby let the wave subside I lose
nothing thereby when the ocean where the
waves come up in the ocean does the
ocean increase no when the waves subside
back into the ocean does it has the
ocean lost any volume of water no in the
same way let Birth come creation come I
have not increased one bit as existence
let defeat humiliation old age disease
decay and death come and destruction
come I have not lost one bit and still
exists aim existence ever this think
about the grandness and the claim is you
can actually experience next he says
those who understand the difference
between the truth these two he says near
Ania the conviction clarity such sadaiva
Assad Assad Ava he says the reality is
real this the assert the appearance is
an appearance I the pure existence
consciousness I am real that one that I
and the body mind including the ego and
the body and external universe is an
appearance appearance of what of me in a
sense all this is an appearance in a
sense all this is me if you say this is
real then yes it is real as you because
it's reality depends on you it's
borrowed from you but remember by you I
don't mean this person I mean that sense
of business awareness such shit which we
continuously experience in all our
experiences then what do you have to do
to warm up it up to darshan Amrit a
mushrik giasses or Arjuna here Shankara
is pitching in to help Krishna he's
saying the Krishna Arjuna should what
should he do take up this viewpoint take
up this viewpoint that's other she means
a knower of reality take up the
viewpoint of the knower of reality in
your life show come o hamsa hatre arise
above delusion and sorrow
I am asan Eva all the waves that come in
your life say that they are appearances
like marici jolivet like the water of a
mirage Monessen is chitchat addictions
were with this clarity with this
conviction he says go back to the
earlier verse he said all the
afflictions in life what had he said was
the solution
he said put up with them how will you
put up with them with this clarity and
conviction this is how you live your
life and do whatever has to be done it
gives you enormous freedom nothing here
is thinking that Professor a lady in the
university invaluable it excites kid but
what she said was the entire universe of
you know objective and objective
entities is contained in one inclusive
within the boundaries of one inclusive a
perspective ground of consciousness but
so this is what what he's saying I'll
end with one monk I know in the
Rishikesh how did one so there was a
great teacher he was teaching about
Vedanta and he didn't know much about
modern science so somebody had shown him
an x-ray and he said I saw this o monks
we were all sitting around all monks
many dekha I saw this a light which goes
through the skin and the blood and the
flesh into the bones to the very bones
this is exactly like this I loved the
way he would bring all these examples
back to vivant exactly like this should
be your vision and like super vision
Superman not to see through to the bones
he says see through to reality he says
maja smokey Drishti I see who nature
here the the vision the perspective it
is nothing to do with the physical
vision your perspective the perspective
of a monk of a practitioner of
non-dualism should be like this keep
your attention on the unchanging reality
and enjoy the movie they've ever ever
changing waves of the ocean which you
are you are the ocean why are you so
worried about little waves rise above
the left
nothing can have effective it can affect
the body but you're not the body the
body is a wave in you instead of
thinking I'm a tiny spark of tiny spark
of consciousness in an uncaring vast
universe of eternal time and space all
the time and all the space and all the
conscious and non conscious entities are
little waves and bubbles in you this is
not megalomania it says it it can it is
actually an open secret we kind of
called it an open secret continuously
available to us it requires a change in
perspective today towards the end after
the end of the discussion in the
university one problem the philosophers
had the lady who presented it did a good
job but see the she gave examples of
Ramana Maharshi and a circa that than
others in that mystic experience they
have experienced the oneness I mean poor
moment you say that what happens is the
evidence then becomes locked up in the
hands of a few people the question will
be why should I believe you
somebody was repeatedly asking this is
an enormous claim you're making where is
the evidence for this there is another
approach which Shankar Acharya uses here
I'm not talking about mystical
experience you will have that also take
a completely analytical point of view
take a completely analytical point of
view that will reveal an ever revealed
reality here the non duelists in the
Himalayas they say prop thus your
property in every toss in everything
what will be done to do to you what will
you get from Vedanta what you have
already got it gives you what you have
already got and what does be done to
remove what problem does it solve it
solves a problem that was never there
practice you prob trapped in every
decision everything yeah yes how did you
go there
you're right you're right that's the
ultimate answer but how do you even
interested in doing up why yes so the
plays the material cause of the pot in
the same way Brahman is said to be the
material cause of this universe but you
said Brahman is not the cause of the
universe why did you say that ah you're
right if it's an appearance see if if
something a seed germinated and it made
a beautiful plant so you can say the
seed is the cause of the plant correct
it's a material which became the plant
but you say the seed made a beautiful
plant where is it now in my dreams if
you say the plant is in my dreams
then you will say the seed that seed is
not the cause of the plant in your
dreams because that plan does not exist
so if the universe is an appearance then
the question will arise what is Brahman
a cause of what did it produce what did
it create nothing Brahman alone remains
there is no universe that was created
there's no universe that was created but
it is experienced that's the joy of it
when King Kong comes and climbs the
Empire State Building
I saw the movie when I was a kid now all
of that happened you had the experience
but actually King Kong did not come into
the movie Hall no in the same wave what
happens here is an experience created by
your Maya it's your glory within you the
existence consciousness so is Brahman
materially a causal universe is it a
creator god no it is the universe and it
is you yes
from Ramon's perspective right no time
no space in fact when you say eternal
Brahman is eternal you've already
accepted time and then you say it but
actually even time look at the logic
will you say time is the moment you say
time is then the easeness becomes real
and it's appearing as time space if you
see space is space depends on isness
because without is space will disappear
you might say people might say it's a
word game you're playing
no because continuously the reference is
to your experience look at your own
experience how can you say it's a word
game so this Brahman you are that is the
central teaching that Krishna is giving
Arjuna now there are many many issues
which will come up here yes so that will
be discussed 18 chapters are there
plenty of time down - yes we'll end with
that question yes so you step down one
one step then Brahman this very Brahman
becomes what is called in Vedanta the
saguna brahman which is a creator of the
universe which through the power of Maya
doesn't create exactly projects the
universe if you want an explanation but
where Dante will tell you that's the
story if you want a story yes what we
want to tells you is all the things in
the dream which you see in your dream
the people and the plans and the places
where they really created by you or
imagined by you
they were imagined by you so you're not
really their creator in that sentinels
know things were created they're
projected by you in your own mind all
the time when you see those places when
you meet those people in your dreams
they're none other than you similarly
this entire universe which we are
thing is none other than Brahman if it
was other than Brahman if it's at all
possible then you could say Brahman
created something apart from itself but
it did not and it cannot be other than
Brahman can you tell me why if Brahman
is easy then other than Brahman will
become isn't a hottie yes you're good
good with an thing sir
other than is is not apart from eases is
not will not will exist will not exist
at all yes the question of why why this
has come up again and again why there
are many many answers I'll give you a
few to take your pick will end with that
it's a very profound question in fact
today in the university and one place it
got stuck is so that you are saying this
is one again the same thing a
perspectival ground of consciousness yes
and from that the many have come how why
and she was struggling to answer that
and it's it's unfair to expect somebody
to answer that immediately what we have
been struggling over for thousands of
years immediately but you see what's the
the beauty is this all the questions the
difficult ones also are exactly the
right questions to ask that means for
the first time in New York University it
will the top philosophers of the world
they are going through a question/answer
process on the track we've here
thousands of years ago Advaita in
Tibetan Buddhists then the duelists who
are opponents of the other way things
they are having the exact same debate
with the exact same questions only in
Sanskrit so your question is why I'll
give you a few candidates see if you
like it one is the theory of the most
standard answer is given karma what does
this world exist because of your own
karma our collective karma where did
this collect collective karma come from
our past lives yeah but where did that
word come from your past life world
because of the earlier life you will see
then where did the first life come from
you'll say no there's no such first life
it's beginningless you'll say it's a
cop-out we are beginning this how can
they have it beginningless there is
answer to that also but let's switch
switch to the next answer the next
answer is it is Brahmins play because it
can Alan Watts I've told you the story
and then what's said God alone existed
it's a child children story but I really
like it a very profound story he said
God alone existed it turned it into
eternity but eternity is a pretty long
time so God got bored it's lonely now
God wanted to play me somebody to play
with
but how can God get somebody to play
with because God is alone this is only
God is nothing else other than God and
there cannot be remember ease will
become is not so how does God get
somebody to play around with who will be
food God's buddy then God being God this
is along a second explanation he's God
is awfully clever because he's God so he
is too got an idea God pretended to be
not God now there are two God and God
pretending to be not God sir the game
started who what's the game there's God
pretending to be not God what's that
people and trees and plants and universe
stars and planets and the problem became
because God is God he's awfully good at
what he does so when he pretended to be
not not God he forgot that he was God
and then what was a play became a
nightmare and now God is who pretending
to be not God and forgotten that he's
God suffering so much he's trying to
search for God and this is the story of
the universe beautiful story really all
of it on top packed into that candidate
would you would you like this story and
you say yeah it's poetic but playing God
please why would God want to play all
right now we are getting serious one
more option the last but one is what the
standard answered in a greater Miya Miya
so God has this power which allows God
let's not use the word Gard Brahmin
isness has this power which allows
isness to appear as many forms clock is
table is sky is earth is water is man is
mind these thoughts
easiness appears in all these forms of
business has that power to project
itself it's like a blank screen which
has the power to project movies upon it
self-consciousness can have that power
that is the nature of consciousness now
what is the question will arise then is
it non-dual how can that power does that
power exists or does it not if it does
not exist you cannot have the universe
if it exists then are two things which
are isness and power is but that power
has no existence apart from isness so
it's non dual it's like they call it
like the fire and the burning power of
fire that's an explanation you might say
even then why infinite existence could
the physicist Lawrence Krauss said this
is children's question they keep asking
why why why till the last solution is go
to bed but Vedanta does not say go to
bed
it says the question itself is wrong if
you ask why Maya the question itself is
wrong why is the question now it took me
a long time to understand Shankar
Acharya Vivekananda they all dismiss it
question is wrong why is the question
wrong I can ask why and so saying go to
bed there is an answer to that look at
what you're asking this is about
causation you're asking because you are
asking why Maya but what is Maya
according to Vedanta - Maya is time
space causation now suppose you ask you
keep it's wrong because you cannot ask
why why when you ask why what kind of
answer will serve will satisfy you a
cause why did it ray why is the grass
wet because it rained why did it rain
because of the clouds and so on so when
you say why Maya you need a because
answer why did Brahman become the
universe or even appear as the universe
why is Brahman even playing if you're
asking that
what answer will satisfy you a because
answer but because answer works only
after causation if you ask a question
about causation itself
why causation it's not a cut logically
correct question why for example time
space and causation it's like asking
what is there outside space outside and
inside our space terms once you have
accepted space then you can ask outside
or inside but space itself what is
outside is nowhere for and outside means
some space is there outside but no time
if you ask what was there before time
but before and after a time words they
make sense only when time is started so
only when causation is started downwards
after Maya then the question is why this
thing happened why that thing happened
but why Maya happened why did Brahman
appear as the universe question itself
is logically wrong am i making logical
sense if not psychological sense but
logical sense it makes logical sense are
you do you see I'll make psychological
sense also Swami three gunas eternal
they give a beautiful answer the same
question was asked he said his answers
immortal it's a really deeply spiritual
answered he said on this side of my on
this side of enlightenment we have the
question and there is no answer possible
on the other side they have the answer
but no question is there
notice enlightened people anybody you
consider to be enlightened Ramana
Maharshi or any circuit that the lady
who start speaking about them all
Ramakrishna Vivekananda one thing I've
ever noticed
do they ever say okay I'm enlightened
now I am a knower of Brahman I'm free
and all of that but one problem still
remains why this thing has happened this
seemed to have the question seems to
have disappeared for them we'll end here
Shanti Shanti Shanti he hurry he own
that's at Sri Ramakrishna repair now
must in fact the answer that lady gave
the professor was the final answer which
I did not mention we'll just quickly
mention it to go to father in a
monocoque arica he considers all these
answers why Brahman is appearing as the
universe and he rejects them all
including the Maya and then finally he
comes to Davis CA Schwab how I am this
is the very nature of the shining one
there is no doubt that his Ness is there
that's the reality and there's no doubt
we are experiencing this variety so that
if isness is shining forth in all these
ways it's a very nature of that this is
not what she said she said in this way
she said this question comes because we
think of that reality as an emptiness
but in all the Scriptures it is thought
of as a plenum as an infinity as
everything is there in an unexpressed
straight and then it gets expressed you
asking why does the Sun Shine so very
nature the process of fusion produces
heat and light same of about Raman
it's a very nature of Brahman to shine
forth in all these ways okay